THE YOUTHFUL MARTYR.

In the days of the young king, Edward the Sixth, a Bible was placed on a desk in every church of the land, for the use of the people. A copy in large print, bound in wooden boards, with curious iron clasps, was then seen fastened by a chain to a strong upright stand. As " the word of God was precious in those days''—for it was costly and scarce, and many truly loved it—those who had a small share of learning read it aloud to those who had less abil- ity than themselves. Thus light began to spread, when a dark cloud came over this hopeful state of things; for queen Mary, astern papist, ascended the throne of England, and quickly ordered the removal of the Bibles. In a few places, however, her com- mands were either not received or were not obeyed.

Whatever was the cause, it is certain that there still lay the old Bible on a stand just inside the porch of the little chapelry at Brentwood, in Essex, England.

It was in the spring of the year 1555, that a youth, named William Hunter, entered the church to read the book he loved. He was an apprentice [64] to a London weaver, but was now on a visit to his native town. The lad was one of those who were faithful to the truth, and who would rather suffer for it, than sin against it. As he stood reading the holy book, and lifting up his heart in prayer, a man of the name of Atwell, a summoner or officer of the popish bishop, came that way, and saw him so engaged. " Why meddlest thou with the Bible V said the officer, not a little angry that a boy should dare to open the Book of God. Knowest thou how to read ? And canst thou expound the Scriptures The youth modestly replied, Father Atwell, I take not upon me to expound the Scriptures; but finding the Bible here, I read it for my comfort.,' The officer then began to speak scornfully of the sacred word as a hurtful book. Say not so,,' said William, in a kind and re- spectful manner, "it is God's book, out of which every one that hath grace may learn to know what pleaseth God, and what is displeasing to him.', Could we not tell formerly,' ' inquired Atwell, as well as now, how God was to be served Not so well as now,'' added William, "if we might have his blessed word among us still, as we have had ; and I pray God that we may have the blessed Bible among us continually." As Atwell could not prevail with the lad, he cried, "I see you are one who dislikes the queen's [65] laws. I have heard how you* left London on that account ; but if you do not turn, you, as well as many other heretics, will broil for your opinions. " God give me grace," meekly replied William, that I may believe his word, and confess his name, whatever may come of it." Confess his name shouted old AtwelL "No, no, you will go to the devil, all of you.,' Atwell quickly left the chapel, and meeting a priest, returned with him to where William was reading, when the priest began to upbraid and threaten him. The youth well knew what this meant, so he hastened to his father's house, and taking a hasty leave of his parents fled from the town. It was a sad time when the young who loved the Lord had to leave the homes of their early days, and seek their dwelling and food wherever they could find them.

A few days after William had gone, a justice sent for the father, and ordered him to produce his son. "What, sir,'' said the parent, would you have me seek my son, that he may be burned The justice was resolute ; and upon this errand the poor father was obliged to depart. He rode about for two or three days, hoping to satisfy the justice without finding his son. The lad, however, saw his father at a distance, and went to meet him. On learning the danger of his parent he said he would return, rather than place his father in any peril.

[66] And yet how could the aged parent secure his own safety by the surrender of his child? It was a struggle of affection : at length he yielded, and they went together into the town. When the evening drew on, William and his father ascended the hill that leads to the little town of Brentwood. The cottagers bade them good cheer as they passed them on their way ; but it was with heavy hearts and weeping eyes that they looked for- ward to the coming morrow. They had not, how ever, to wait till the morning dawn, for during the night the young Christian was seized, and hurried to the stocks. There he lay, till break of day, pained in body, but happy in mind.

Early in the morning, William was taken before a justice of the peace, who, after trying in vain to shake his faith, ordered him to be carried to the old palace in the fields of Bethnal Green—about sixteen miles away—where Bonner, the popish bishop of London, then resided. When he stood in the hall of the palace, the bishop first spoke to him gently, then sternly, and then roughly ; but still the youth would not promise to give up the Bible, and deny its truths. " Away with him again to the stocks,, , cried the bishop, and to the stocks William was again hurried. Two long days and nights he there lay, without any food, except a crust of brown bread and a small supply of water. Poor boy, what were his thoughts in these hours of trial ? Alone, [67] oppressed, and with the prospect of a painful death before him, what did he suffer? What were the prayers and cries which then went up to God from his heart ? Surely he had grace given to him to bear all with humble trust and patience ; or, like Paul and Silas, as he felt the pressure of the wood on his legs, he may have sung praises unto God. We can- not but believe that his Saviour, who tenderly feels for his suffering disciples, gave to him to taste his choicest comfort and love. Not satisfied with this act of cruelty, his enemies proceeded to further lengths, in the hope of sub- duing his spirit. The bishop sent illiam to one of the London prisons, with strict orders to the jailer to put as many iron chains upon him as he could possibly bear. And in a dungeon he was confined for three-quarters of a year, hoping, trust- ing, praying always.

Bishop Bonner one day thought of the Bible- loving lad in prison, and hoping that his long con- finement, together with the natural love of liberty and home, had made him more ready to yield, sent for him to his palace. But the spirit of the young martyr was yet unbroken, and his trust in the gos pel as firm as before. "If you recant,', said the bishop, "I will give you forty pounds, and set you up in business. This was a large sum of money in those days, and the offer was very tempting, but it was at once rejected.

[68] "I will make you steward of my own house," added Bonner, in a gentle and crafty manner.

"But, my lord," was the reply, "If you cannot persuade my conscience by Scripture, I cannot find in my heart to turn from God for the love of the world ; for I count all worldly things but loss, in comparison with the love of Christ." Will neither threats nor promises avail ? Then away with him to the fire. When William again entered his native town, he knew it was to endure a painful death. But yet he knew what his Saviour had suffered for him. And he remembered, too, the words, " Be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life.'' There was no prison in the little town, so the mar tyr youth was confined in an inn, and guarded by constables. His mother heard of his return, and with true love rushed to the place where he lay. Charity moved the hearts of the guards, and they allowed her to see him, and to sit by his side. And when she found him happy and constant, she bless- ed God for such a son, and the more so when he said: "For my little pain which I shall sufi'er, Christ hath procured for me a crown of joy ; are you not glad of that, mother ?" They then knelt down and she prayed to God to strengthen her poor boy to the end. At length the morning came that young William was to die. The sherifi", justices, and priests were duly in attendance, with executioners and guards, [69] while a crowd of people had come together, to the last sad scene. As the young martyr was led along from the inn, his father rushed forward towards him in an agony of parental feeling. Throwing his arms around the neck of his noble son, he said, with flowing tears, God be with thee, son William.,' The son calmly looked for the last time on his dear parent, and replied, God be with you, father; THE YOUTHFUL MARTYR. be of good comfort; I trust we shall meet again where we shall rejoice together.

There were many weeping eyes on that day in 7 [70] the little town of Brentwood. To see one so young —a kind, gentle, pious lad—dragged through the streets to bear the scorching flames, whose only offence was that he loved the gospel, was a sight that touched the hardest heart, and brought tears on many a manly cheek. William, as he passed along, saw his father's cottage, and cast a last look on his sorrowing sisters. He bade farewell to those who had been the playmates and friends of his ear liest days. He was now to suffer in the cause of Christ, and they saw that he feared not to die. At last, the procession came to the end of the town, where the stake and chain and fagots were ready.

Without loss of time he was secured by the chain, and wood was piled around. While this was being done, a pardon was offered if he would profess him self a papist.

"No,'' said William, resolutely, "I will not re- cant, God willing. Then turning to the people he asked them to pray for him. " Pray for thee cried a hard-hearted justice who was looking on, I will no more pray for thee than I would for a dog.'' "I pray Grod this may not be laid to your charge at the last day," was William's calm reply.

A priest, too, began to taunt him ; until a gentle- man spoke aloud, May God have mercy on his soul;" and the people mournfully added, Amen." The fire was now lighted, and as the flames began [71] to rise, William, who still held in his hand a book of Psalms, threw it into the hands of his brother, who had followed him to the place of death. His brother calling to him said, William, think on the sufferings of Christ, and be not afraid." "I am not afraid,'' added the martyr. "Lord, Lord, receive my spirit." These were his last words. The fire was lighted; the dry fagots burned briskly; and the flames soon wrapped around his body. In a few minutes his sufferings were at an end for ever.

THE martyr's tree, BRENTWOOD. An old elm tree still marks the spot, near which William Hunter yielded up his life for the truth.

[72] Though three hundred years have passed since then, his name is not forgotten. His soul has joined the noble army of martyrs', in heaven ; but the record of his faith and courage will long survive on earth. Let us learn from his history:—1. The import- ance of early decision in the cause and service of Christ; as a preservative in times of error and false religion.

2. The need of constancy in resisting the most tempting offers to deny our Master. Like Moses the servant of God, let us choose rather to suffer aflSiction with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season; esteeming the re- proach of Christ greater riches than the treasures in Egypt.- 3. The blessing of having pious parents. The father and mother of William could give up such a son to Christ for Christ, encouraging him, even in the prospect of death, not to renounce the truth. May your parents never be called to such a test of love.

4. The true character of Popery. Can that be the pure and holy religion of Jesus—the religion of love and mercy—which commits such dreadful deeds ? Christ was kind and loving to all. He came "not % to destroy men,s lives, but to save them.- When his disciples would have used the sword, and have called " down fire from heaven,- he rebuked them.

How different from his gentle and merciful spirit has been the conduct of cruel persecutors in every age !

THE MAIDEN MARTYR.

More than two hundred and fifty years have pass- ed since a Spaniard thus wrote of his native land : —"In Spain, many very learned, many very no ble, and many of the highest gentry, have for this cause'' (that of the reformed faith) been led forth to the scaffold. There is not a city, and, if one may so speak, there is not a village, nor a hamlet, nor a noble house in Spain, that has not had, and still has, one or more that God of his infinite mercy has enlightened with the light of his gospel. Our ene- mies have done what they could to put out this light, and thus they have visited with loss of pro perty, of honor, and of life, very many in Spain.

And yet it is worthy of note, the more they threat en, scourge, throw into the galleys, imprison, or burn, the more they multiply.'' * The good work had been begun and carried on chiefly by the means of Bibles and tracts. Although the Inquisition kept strict watch and strong guard, to prevent all books from entering the land, it was so managed, that they were carried from the border * De Castro's Spanish ProteatantR. 7* [74] towns to those in the interior, in bales of goods, and were gladly bought by all classes. And thus the work of the Reformation went silently and steadily on. But cloudy days indeed have come over the country of Spain since the times of which we speak; the light has been put out, and gross darkness covers the people.

One of the cities in which the gospel took the deepest root was Seville, a place of great wealth and trade, and famous for its noble palaces, beautiful churches and ancient dwellings.

Among its other buildings there once stood a long and lofty range, whose gloomy walls and iron- barred windows marked it as a prison. The passen ger, as he drew nigh to it, quickened his pace, and trembled at the thought that he might one day be shut up in its dreary cells. This place was the court of the Inquisition, so called, because it was the tribunal set up to inquire into the opinions of any who were inclined to renounce the religion of the land. This court sent forth a class of monks as its agents, known as the inquisitors, or inquirers, to search out and punish all those who did not prompt ly submit to the creed of Popery. The steps of these inquisitors took hold on death. Few who went into their presence returned again to their homes. Fires were kindled by them, and many faithful servants of Christ were cast into the flames.

[75] Others had trial of cruel mockings, and scourg ings, yea, moreover, of bonds and imprisonment." The unhappy victim who passed the iron gate of the Inquisition was led through several halls, one opening into the other, and each increasing in dark ness, until the last was shrouded in dismal shadows. A single window looked into the yard below, around which were ranged the entrances to the cells, sunk far below the surface of the ground. The descent into these was by many winding ways, that from their depths the cries of the prisoners might not be heard. The sweet light and pure air of heaven entered not there. All was black, and damp, and terrific. In some of these vaults human bones were spread on the ground, and the walls were covered with the names of those who had been left to perish, unpitied and unknown. There were cruel and wicked deeds done in those silent vaults, in the name of the holy and merciful Saviour, which, could we know them fully, would fill our hearts with shame and horror. The assistants to the inquisitors were called familiars; that is, those attached to the family', or order of monks. In the darkness of the night these familiars suddenly stood before the door of a house, with their faces entirely covered with a hood, in which were two small holes for the eyes. No one dared to resist their power, or to assist the object of their search in his escape. It might be [76] that they had got a father to inform against his wife, or a mother against her son, or a brother against a sister ; for all the bonds of love and duty were broken by their craft. It was enough if any one were suspected of having read, or lent, or kept in the house a book of the reformed faith; or had a Protestant for a friend, or had tried to console and aid a prisoner in the cells. They had now come for the unhappy person in an hour when he was at rest. The door must instantly be opened, and at once they seize him, and carry him away to their dungeons. There, perhaps, to lie for many months, in awful suspense, wearied and worn, before he knew the charge that he was called to answer. Among those who had been seized by the servants of the Inquisition, and brought before its court, was a young Spanish lady, named Maria de Bohorques, the daughter of a gentleman of high condition in Seville, and related to several noble families. Her early youth was full of hope and promise, and her home was cheered by every earthly comfort. But she had been led by divine grace to give her heart to Christ, and set her affections on. things above. Maria, when about twenty-one years of age, was suspected of being faithless to the church of Rome.

Her tutor. Doctor Gil, who had been led to embrace the reformed faith, was one of the most learned men of the age. Under his care she had studied the Holy Scriptures in their original languages. A [77] blessing had attended the reading of the word of God; and her gifted and inquiring mind had found the only foundation on which true religion rests. She was not long in learning that the Roman Cath olic religion is contrary to the truth of God, and she had courage to make known what she knew and felt.There were times when Maria thought of the terrible Inquisition. In her hours of secret study and prayer, she had asked of God to give her strength, if the day of trial which had come to many should at last reach her. And now it had come, and she stood alone and undefended before her judges.

The maiden martyr was led by the officers into a secret chamber, where at a table sat the inqui sitors, clad in dark robes, their faces scarcely to be seen, from the position in which they sate, amid the deep gloom of the place. Before them was a small wooden cross, and a roll of paper inscribed with the charge against the prisoner. By their side were guards and witnesses. Soft words were at first spoken. They told her that they wished well to her soul ; that they hoped to restore a stray sheep to the fold. As she listened • to their address, Maria prayed in her heart, and strength was given her to be faithful. She boldly owned her hope in the gospel of Jesus Christ, and refused to yield to the smooth speeches or the angry [78] threats of her judges. They then declared that, unless she submitted to the church of Rome, she should be tried by torture. And to awaken terror in the mind of the young Christian, there were spread out to view the engines of cruelty used in that horrid chamber. She was pointed to the pulley, by which a prisoner was raised to the roof of the dungeon, with heavy weights fastened to the feet ; to the rack, on which the body was violently • stretched ] to the fire, over which the feet of the sufferers were hung.

The judges were concerned to know who were her [79] companions in the faith, and called on her to make them known. But she gave no reply. Again they directed her eyes to the instruments of torture, with a threat of their severest trial. Still she stood firm ly in her resolve. The order was now given to stretch her upon the rack : and, like wolves greedy for their prey, the officers seized her, and casting her on the frame, they secured her wrists and feet to the cords. In a few minutes the slow turn of the wheel drew her tender limbs, as though they would be torn from her body. In this position of agony Maria was again called on to confess; but the bold girl refused to renounce her own faith or betray those she loved. Another turn of the cruel wheel was made, and her joints seemed to start from their sockets. Poor lonely one !

the men in whose hands she had fallen had no hearts to feel; to them mercy was unknown. Great as was her misery, and wh,n she thought it had reached its height, it was as though it only had be- gun. New seats of pain were reached, and in the depth of her woe she called for pity.

Perhaps many have said to themselves, If we were called to be martyrs we would show our perse- , cutors how to die." But how little do we know our own weakness ! In the hour of her greatest pain, when scarcely sensible of what she said, poor Maria owned that her sister Juana had often spoken to her about the reformed faith, and was a secret [80] follower of it. This confession soon cost Juana her life ! To the rack she was quickly brought, and on being removed from it, she lay for a short time in the greatest agony, and then died. But Maria—what had she done ? She felt that she had been faithless to the cause she loved. She had betrayed one dearer to her than her own life. When they took her from the wheel, they carried her to a cell. It was sweet to her to lie on that cold stone floor, and feel that the wheel was no longer dragging her life away. Yet she had only gained a short release at the expense of a beloved sister. Another day of trial was at hand. Maria was soon doomed to the flames as. a heretic; but before the sentence was carried into effect, two priests were sent to her, then another two, and again two more. They went to her cell in the hope that she might yet yield, and profess *her faith in the church of Rome.

It must have been an affecting sight to have be- held that poor young creature—her limbs all bruised and full of intense pain—without any human friend —reclining on the straw of her cell, while she meek ly and piously disputed with the crafty priests. She heard their words in patience, and then calmly re- fused to receive their doctrine. Hour after hour they tried all their art and power, but in vain. She told them of her weakness in suffering; but yet she [81] looked to God for grace to bear all, and to go bold ly to the burning pile rather tban deny the truth she loved. On the morning of the 24th of September, 1559, more than one fatal stake was driven in the great square of the city of Seville. A number of the THE GREAT SQUARE OF SEVILLE. reformed faith were to be burned that day. Among them was Maria de Bohorques. Early in the morn ing the officers came to her cell, to carry her to the place of death, for the torture had deprived her of the power to walk. Feeble in body, she was 8 [82] yet strong in heart. Her inward strength was made perfect in weakness and suffering. The Lord was with her; she " endured, as seeing Him who is in visible." Her looks betrayed no fear. Ifc was to her a day of victory and deliverance. Through the flames she knew that she should pass to glory.

There were other female Protestants burned in Seville's great square at the same time, and Maria sought to comfort her sister martyrs. She invited them to join with her in singing a hymn. And above the noise and tumult of the crowd, there assembled, their sweet voices were heard sounding the praises of the Saviour. They then cheered one another as they stood ready for death.

It was usual at such a time, when the victims were bound to the stake, and the torch was about to be applied to the wood, for one more attempt to be made to induce the prisoner to confess. For this purpose several priests, oUt of regard to the youth, talent and family connections of Maria, tried yet again to bring her to renounce her faith. She was asked to repeat the creed, and this she did in a firm voice ; but, at the same time, she explained its several parts in the Protestant sense. Finding that they gained nothing by their attempts, the officers were ordered to strangle her. This done, the pile was soon lighted, and her body was consumed.

Her released spirit passed beyond the reach of her tormentors, there to receive the martyr's crown [83] from the hands of her Lord and Saviour—a crown which he purchased with his own most precious blood, and which is the rich gift of his grace and love. As we fondly cherish the memory of those who "loved not their lives unto death," we may well direct our thoughts to their happy state now in the world of glory.

Who are they, clothed in radiant white, That stand around yon golden throne : Their garments of celestial light. Pare with a lustre not their own ? These are the saints, who once below Walked in the path their Master trod ; Midst pain, and mockery and woe, And scorching flames, they sought their God. Through His dear might who once was slain, Firm at the burning stake they stood, And washed, from every guilty stain, Their garments in his precious blood. Therefore around the throne they stand, And in his holy temple shine ; Rich in the joy of his right hand, Robed in his righteousness divine. There they can never hunger more, Nor ask the cooling draught in vain ; For He will living waters pour. And heal from every earthly pain. In those blessed realms of endless day. The Lamb shall all their wants supply ; And God's own hand shall wipe away The falling tear from every eye.

THE FORFEITED CROWN.

On the 6th of February, 1685, the heralds pro- claimed before the new palace at Whitehall, that James the Second had succeeded to the crown of England. Coaches, filled with noble ladies, lined the streets. Gentlemen were in groups, on foot or horseback. Flags were hung from house and steeple.

Guns were fired at the Tower ; the church bells rung merrily, the drums and trumpets sounded, while crowds of people shouted forth their loyalty, making one mingled din, that passed from street to street, till the whole town was in an uproar.

It was known that James was a Papist ; but then he had promised fair things ; and the nation hoped that he would respect their religion and laws. "We have the word of a king,'' said the most loyal, "and a king will not break his word.'' " We have our fears," said others, but we trust all will be for the best." How James kept his promise, and what deeds were done by his command, the page of history will tell us.

[154] It is only three weeks after the king has come to the throne, that an aged man of calm and gentle looks stands before a judge to answer a charge of sedition. It is good Richard Baxter, who has long preached Christ,s gospel, and bj his writings has led many souls to Christ. On the bench sits judge Jeflfreys—a base, bad man, an enemy to freedom, truth, and purity—one ever ready to carry out the designs of a tyrant king.

The prisoner has been carried from a bed of sick- ness to the court, and he asks for time to meet the charge. " I will not give him a minute to save his life,'' cries the judge. We have had to do,'' adds he mockingly, " with other sorts of persons ; but now we have a saint to deal with, and I know how to deal with saints as well as sinners.'' The counsel for the prisoner rises to .appeal on his behalf ; and as he speaks of the peaceable spirit of Baxter, who is known to all as a well-wisher to the royal family, the judge shouts aloud, He is an old blockhead—an unthankful villain—the spring of faction—a stubborn dog." Hang him," he cries, or let him be whipped through the streets.*' Baxter is about to speak again, when Jeffreys stops him. Richard ! Richard ! Dost thou think we will hear thee poison the court? Thou hast written books enough to load a cart ; and every one is full of sedition as an egg is full of meat. Hadst thou been whipped out of thy writing trade forty [155] years ago, it had been happy. I will crush you. Now, speak up ; what do you say for yourself "I am ready to produce my writings,'' is Baxter's answer ; and my life and conduct are known to many in this nation." Fury sits in the looks of the judge, who again loads him with reproaches, while the prisoner, turning to those who stand by his side, points to some clergymen who have boldly appeared this day to speak to his loyal and holy life. There is not an honest man in England," shouts JeiFreys in a perfect rage, "but who takes thee to be a great knave." The mock trial is at length over; and Baxter is sent to prison, where he must lie till happier times shall dawn upon the land. *,When I saw," says an eye-witness, "the meek man standing before the flaming eyes and fierce looks of this judge, I thought of Paul standing before the king. The cruel usage he received drew plenty of tears from my eyes, as well as from others of the spectators." The king of England has no power to make or set aside any law but with the consent of parlia- ment. This did not suit the proud will of James the Second. He was resolved to favor the interests of the Roman Catholics, and issued a decree con trary to the law. This decree, or ',declaration," [156] the clergy were ordered to read in the churches. The archbishop of Canterbury and six bishops hastened to the palace, and presented a petition to the king on their knees, begging him to withdraw his command. But they were rudely spurned from his presence. In a few days a barge was seen passing down the river Thames, in which were the seven bishops.

They were on their way to prison. Around them were other boats, filled with the guards. Crowds of people were on the banks ; some were kneeling and begging a blessing from the prisoners as they moved along, while the air rang with shouts. The bishops were shortly brought to trial. The charge was that they had refused to obey the king.

From early morning till late in the evening, the trial went on. At night the jury were locked up in darkness. Early the next day they came into court with the verdict of " not guilty.,' And then up rose a shout of joy that made old Westminster hall ring again. The throng without caught the sound, and sent it rolling along the street. A crowd of people waited to see the bishops come forth, and when they appeared another shout, louder than ever, was heard, which rose and fell like the breakers on the sea-shore. All London seemed to share in the joy; and as the bishops returned to their homes the people fell on their knees once more; the bells rang, and at night bonfires were lighted in every open space.

[157] King James was at Hounslow reviewing the troops, and, on hearing a great noise, asked, What was the matter Nothing but the soldiers shouting for the acquittal of the bishops.', Call you that nothing he asked ; but never mind, it will be so much the worse for them,,' he proudly added.

It was soon seen that the great aim of king James was to discourage and oppress the Protes tants, and to set up the papacy as the great power in the land. On the second Sunday after he came to the throne he went in his state coach, with great pomp, to the royal chapel, and ordered the doors to be set wide open while mass was performed. When he was crowned he took care that the communion service after a Protestant form should be omitted. Two papers in support of the doctrines of the church of Rome were printed by his desire, and sent through the land; while, on the other hand, the bishops and clergy were commanded not to preach against the church of Rome. An agent was sent to the pope, to present the homage of the king; and, in return, an ambassador came from Rome, and was received with much honor. The highest officer in the university of Cambridge was dismissed, because he would not carry out the popish views of the king; and at Oxford many of the college tutors were deprived of their places for resisting an at- 14* [158] tempt to force on them a papist as their head. Monasteries were set up; and such numbers of priests and monks flaunted through the streets in their robes, that the king boasted he had made the towns and cities of England like those in papal lands. Nor did the king stop here. Many oflGicers of State who would not change their religion, were re- placed by strict Papists—some of whom were men of low habits, and wholly unfit to serve the country.

A priest and two Roman Catholic noblemen became his chief advisers in every matter. He sought to compel his daughter, the princess Anne, to join the church of Rome ; and next to deprive his eldest daughter Mary, the wife of the prince of Orange, of her right as heir to the throne because she was a Protestant. At last, he carried matters to such a point, that even the Spanish ambassador warned him of his danger. Does not your master consult with priests asked the king. "Yes,'' was the reply, and that is the reason why our country's affairs go on so badly.

The heavy hand of a tyrant was felt to be on the liberties of the country. The king levied taxes in his own name, and claimed a right to put aside the laws of the land by his own power. Four thousand Protestant soldiers were refused their pay, and sent to wander hungry and half-naked through the land. All who were thought to be unfriendly to his doings were fined, whipped, or sent to prison.

[159] The king had not sat long on his throne, when the news was spread that the duke of Monmouth, the king's nephew, and the .earl of Argyle, had raised the flag of rebellion. But their plans were rash and badly managed. They had no money, no arms, nor any promise of support from the people.

The king's troops soon overthrew them, and the lives of these two noblemen were forfeited. Now was a time for the king to show mercy to the followers of the rebel chiefs. By such a course he might win the hearts of many, and turn the tide in his favor. One of the prisoners was brought be fore him. You know it is in my power,'' said the king, to pardon you.'' Yes," said the man, who well knew his cruel character, but it is not in your nature." However unwise this answer was, its truth was soon seen. Judge Jeffreys was sent with a troop of soldiers to punish all rebels, and every one who had shown them any favor. Among others was a pious and aged woman, lady Alice Lisle, who was charged with hiding two men in her house. She was not aware that they had been in arms against the king; and the jury who tried her felt that there was no proof of guilt. But the king's commands must be obeyed; she must not be spared. The sentence of death was passed, and she went forth to the block in a spirit worthy of her high Christian character. Hundreds of unhappy prisoners, more or less [160] guilty, were hung ia a few days, The country for six miles between Exeter and Bristol," says one who saw the sad scene, ,' had a new and terrible sort of sign post ] the heads of the executed were placed in rows on poles by the road side." Other prisoners were burned alive, and some escaped by paying large bribes. The judges, and other persons in power, had many that were found guilty made over to them as gifts, that they might be sold as slaves, or ransomed at a large price by their friends. Thousands were carried to the West India islands to labor in slavery. Among those condemned to be sold were twenty-seven young ladies at Taunton, whose offence was that they had given a flag and a Bible to the duke of Monmouth. They were saved from slavery by the payment of a great sum, which was divided among the queen's maids of honor as a " Christmas box.'' For weeks Jeffreys went forward in his career of blood. The nation looked on with horror at the terrible doings, and deep and bitter were the feelings that came over men's minds.

While the people were thus borne down they heard that James had received twenty thousand pounds from Louis, king of France, to aid him in his designs. Then the news came that a pitiless war was raging against the Protestants of France, many of whom escaped to England. And as they told of their bitter trials, the people saw what they [161] might expect should James succeed in setting up the Papal religion in the land. All Protestants were alike oppressed by the king. Places of worship were shut up, and ministers dragged to prison. They then met in small numbers in private houses, late in the evening or early in the morning. There were friends who stood at the doors always on the watch to give notice of danger. They made windows or holes in the walls between two houses, that the preacher's voice might be heard in more places than one. They had often secret pas- sages and trap doors for their escape. In country towns and villages they went through back yards and gardens that they might not be noticed. For the same reason they never sang psalms, and the minister was placed in some inward part of the house that his voice might not be heard in the streets. But the time came when men not only whisper ed, but spoke openly of their country's wrongs.

Christian ministers, the officers of the army and navy, and the great body of the people, groaned under their bondage. There was no law but the king's will; no justice or safety in the land. They asked if it were not right in them to maintain their religion and their laws. We have been trodden to the ground," said many; shall we not seek to stand up as free-born Britons ?" Yes," said others, ,' the king has stretched the bow to such a degree that some day it will snap asunder." [162] All eyes were turned to William, prince of Orange, who had married Mary, the eldest daughter of James. He was a man of talent, of good cha racter, and a zealous Protestant. Near to the town of Maidenhead, on the banks of the Thames, stood a mansion, known as Hurley house. It was a fine, old building, around which the river flowed in its winding course, and before it spread out to view a lovely landscape. Often in VAULT UNDER HURLEY-HOUSE. the early part of the year 1688 there met, in a gloomy vault beneath this house, several noblemen and others. They spoke of the helpless and hope- [163] less state of the country under tbe reign of James, and resolved, if he would not grant them redress, to apply to the prince of Orange for aid. Seven of them signed a paper, calling on the prince to come to England, and defend their cause. While the English nobles at home made ready for the conflict, the prince fitted out his ships and collected his troops. By the end of October the Protestant east wind,', as it was called, carried the fleet towards the shores of England.

There were many praying hearts in Britain and Holland that God would grant success to this enter prise. Public feeling was raised to the highest point; and soon was heard from the clifls of Torbay a cry that the ships had reached the English coast. Seven hundred vessels bore the invading army.

On the flag of the prince's ship were the words, I WILL MAINTAIN THE PrOTESTANT RELIGION AND THE LIBERTIES OF ENGLAND.', On the 5th of November, 1688—eighty-four years after the discovery of the popish plot to blow up the Houses of Parliament, on the same day of the month—prince William landed at Torbay amidst the shouts of the people. An ofiicer rode at full speed, bearing the tidings to James at Whitehall. The king turned pale, a letter in his hand fell to the ground, and he stepped aside to weep. James now found what it is to be served only from fear. In the hour of his need he was without [164] one who truly loved him. Nobles and gentry soon joined the ranks of the prince of Orange; and many to whom the king had shown favor deserted him. Opposed by his own son-in-law, betrayed by his courtiers, with an army that could not be trust- ed, and shunned by the people, he tasted the last bitter drop in his cup of grief when he was told that his daughter, the princess Anne, had also fled from him. Then was wrung from him the bitter wail, Oh, help ! my very children have forsaken me.'' Early in the morning of the 11th of December, [165] a common hackney coach left Whitehall. It hurried down to the river side. Two persons stepped from it into a boat awaiting them on the Thames. As they passed by Lambeth, one of them threw a box into the water, and then landing on the opposite shore, they both hurried along the road that led to the county of Kent. In a short time the royal chamber was found empty. The king had fled ! He, and one of his household, were the persons who had crossed the water, and in the box thrown into the stream was the great seal of England.

After passing from town to town, James got on board a small ship, and arrived in France. The pope's ambassador rushed out of London in the dis- guise of a footman; and judge Jeffreys was caught in the dress of a sailor, wearing an old tarred hat, at a low public house in Wapping. A shout of joy was raised by the people when they heard of the capture of thfe wicked man. To sav, him from their fury, he was taken to the Tower of London, where he soon ended his days as a prisoner.

Thus closed the reign of James the Second. It was short, unhonored, and is a blot on the page of English history. From first to last it was without a single event that was for the honor of the king or the happiness of his subjects. By a wise course he might have reigned over a loyal and loving people : 15 [166] but he sought to overthrow the Protestant religion, and to raise a corrupt church on its ruins. It ended in the loss of his crown. On the flight of James, England was without a king or a ruler. The prince of Orange soon called together the peers and those gentlemen who had been members of the last parliament. After solemn debate, it was declared by them that the throne was vacant, that James had forfeited the crown, and that the prince and princess of Orange should be king and queen. They also agreed to a bill of rights,, , which set forth the great principles of the British constitution, and secured to the people many valuable privileges, among which was a merciful and just regard to the laws of the land. The strength of the throne and the freedom of the people of England—the home of our ancestors — were thus provided for. May young Protestants know how to value their civil and religious advan tages, and be grateful to God that the country in which their forefathers were born was saved, in the days of James, from the craft of the church of Rome.